《功夫熊猫》
传奇故事传颂着一名传奇大侠
Legend tells of a legendary warrior…
他的功夫出神入化
…whose kung fu skills were the stuff of legend.
他走遍天涯 独孤求败
He traveled the land in search of worthy foes.
你挺喜欢吃啊 有种吃我一拳
I see you like to chew. Maybe you should chew on my fist!
大侠一言不发 因为吃了个满嘴
The warrior said nothing for his mouth was full.
他一口吞下 这才开口道
Then he swallowed. And then he spoke.
「少废话 接招吧！」
Enough talk. Let's fight!
拿命来！
Shashabooey!
他的一招一式如此彪悍
He was so deadly in fact,
他的敌人目不暇接 瞠目结舌
that his enemies would go blind from overexposure to pure awesomeness.
- 我的眼睛啊！- 他太彪悍啦！
- My eyes! - He's too awesome!
- 太迷人了！- 我们何以回报？
- And attractive. - How can we repay you?
彪悍不求回报
There is no charge for awesomeness.
迷人更无所需
Or attractiveness.
出事了！
Kablooey!
他征战无数
It mattered not how many foes he faced.
无人匹敌
They were no match for his bodacity!
从没有哪只熊猫能让人如此畏惧 又让人如此爱戴
Never before had a panda been so feared! And so loved.
即使是神州大地之上最英勇的勇士们
Even the most heroic heroes in China,
「盖世五侠」
the Furious Five,
也心怀敬意地拜倒在这位大师脚下
bowed in respect to this great master.
一块儿出去玩玩？
We should hang out.
同意
Agreed.
但出去玩的事情得先放一边
But hanging out would have to wait.
因为当你眼前是恶魔山的万千暴徒时
Because when you're facing the 10, 000 demons of Demon Mountain,
正经事只有一件 那就是…
there's only one thing that matters and that's…
阿宝 快起床！
Po! Get up!
要误生意了
You'll be later for work!
啥？
What?
阿宝 快起床！
Po! Get up!
阿宝 你磨蹭啥呢？
Po. What are you doing up there?
没啥
Nothing.
金猴、螳螂、仙鹤、灵蛇、娇虎
Monkey! Mantis! Orane! Viper! Tigress!
阿宝 快点 都误生意了
Po! Let's go! You're late for work.
来啦…
Coming!
对不起 老爸
Sorry, Dad.
对不起可变不出面条来
Sorry doesn't make the noodles.
你在楼上搞什么名堂 稀里哗啦的
What were you doing up there? All that noise.
没什么 就是个乱七八糟的梦
Nothing. I just had a crazy dream.
什么梦？
About what?
梦到什么了？
What were you dreaming about?
梦到了…我梦见了…
What was I…?
我梦见了…
I was dreaming about…
面条
…noodles.
面条？你真梦见面条了？
Noodles? You were really dreaming about noodles?
没错 不然还能梦见啥？
Yeah. What else would I be dreaming about?
小心 汤很锋利哦（有飞镖）
Careful! That soup is sharp.
噢 太让人高兴了！
Oh, happy day!
我儿子终于做了个面条梦了！
My son, finally having the noodle dream!
噢 你不知道 我等这一刻都等了多久
You don't know how long I've been waiting for this moment.
这是个好兆头 阿宝
This is a sign, Po.
什么好兆头
A sign of what?
我终于可以把我的秘之又秘
You are almost ready to be entrusted with the secret ingredient.
私酿密汤的配方传给你了
of my Secret Ingredient Soup.
这样你就能不辱使命 继承这间饭馆了
Then you will fulfill your destiny and take over the restaurant!
就像我子承父业 父承爷业一样
As I took it over from my father who took it over from his father…
这店可是爷爷打麻将从朋友手里赢来的
…who won it from a friend in mahjong.
老爸 老爸 这不过是场梦
Dad, Dad, Dad, it was just a dream.
不 这是启示之梦
No, it was the dream.
我们可是面条世家 连血管里都流着面汤
We are noodle folk. Broth runs through our veins.
可是 老爸 你有没有…想过做点别的
But, Dad, didn't you ever want to do something else?
除了面条之外的
Something besides noodles?
其实 我年少轻狂的时候
Actually, when I was young and crazy,
曾想过 离家出走 学做豆腐
I thought about running away and learning how to make tofu.
那你干吗不做？
Why didn't you?
因为这是个黄梁蠢梦
Because it was a stupid dream.
你能想象我做豆腐的样子吗？
Can you imagine me making tofu?
豆腐？
Tofu.
别提了！我们各有其命
No! We all have our place in this world.
我的命就是在这儿煮面 而你…
Mine is here, and yours is…
我知道 也是在这儿
I know, is here.
错！是送2号桌 5号桌 7号桌 还有12号桌
No, it's at tables 2, 5, 7, and 12.
别忘了微笑服务
Service with a smile.
干得漂亮 徒弟们 要想不让我失望
Well done, students… if you were trying to disappoint me.
娇虎 力道要更强 金猴 速度要更快
Tigress, you need more ferocity! Monkey, greater speed.
仙鹤 凌空要更高 灵蛇 出招要更敏锐 螳螂…
Orane, height. Viper, subtlety. Mantis…
- 师父 - 插什么嘴
- Master Shifu. - What?!
乌龟大师 他想见您
It's Master Oogway. He wants to see you.
乌龟大师 您召见我 是出什么事了吗？
Master Oogway, you summoned me? Is something wrong?
为何非要出事 才能与老友相聚呢？
Why must something be wrong for me to want to see my old friend?
这么说 没出啥事？
So, nothing's wrong?
也不能说没事
Well, I didn't say that.
您是想说…
You were saying?
我看见一些幻相
I have had a vision.
太郞会重现江湖
Tai Lung will return.
这不可能 他还在牢里呢
That is impossible! He is in prison.
一切皆有可能
Nothing is impossible.
小曾
Zeng!
马上飞到桃岗天牢去告诉他们
Fly to Ohorh-Gom prison and tell them,
看守加倍 兵器加倍 统统都加倍
to double the guards, double their weapons, double everything!
绝不能让大龙逃出大牢
Tai Lung does not leave that prison!
遵命！师父大师
Yes, Master Shifu!
古语有云 子欲避之 反促遇之
One often meets his destiny on the road he takes to avoid it.
我们不能无动于衷 我们不能让他闯入谷中泄愤
We must do something! We can't let him march on the valley and take his revenge!
他会…
He'll…
你心如此水 我的朋友
Your mind is like this water my friend.
乱则不明
When it is agitated it becomes difficult to see.
但若心如止水
But if you allow it to settle…
答案便尽现眼前
…the answer becomes clear.
神龙卷轴
The Dragon Scroll.
是时候了
It is time.
可传给谁？谁值得信任 能把这无限的力量交付与他
But who? Who is worthy to be trusted with the secret to limitless power?
让他成为「神龙大侠」
To become the Dragon Warrior?
我也不知道
I don't know.
借过 抱歉
Excuse me. Pardon me. Sorry.
嘿 看着点走 阿宝
Watch it!
对不起 收腹！
Sorry. Suck it up!
对不起 一千个抱歉
Sorry. A thousand pardons.
什么？
What?
乌龟大师要选神龙大侠！就在今天！
Master Oogway's choosing the Dragon Warrior! Today!
大伙们 快去翡翠宫 五侠之一要得到神龙卷轴了！
Everyone! Get to the Jade Palace! One of the Five is gonna get the Dragon Scroll!
千年等一回啊！碗上端快去啊！
We've waited 1, 000 years for this! Take the bowl!
这可是功夫史上最重要的一天 别操心付账了 快去吧！
This is the greatest day in kung fu history! Just go!
阿宝 你要去哪儿？
Po! Where are you going?
去翡翠宫
To the Jade Palace.
可你忘了你的面条车了
You're forgetting your noodle cart.
整个山谷的人都会去 你可以大卖特卖
The whole valley will be there and you'll sell noodles to all of them.
卖面条？
Selling noodles?
可是 老爸 我在想我可不可以…
But, Dad, I was thinking, maybe I…
- 什么？- 我在想我可不可以…
- Yeah? - I was thinking maybe I…
可不可以也顺道卖点豆包 省的放坏了
…could also sell the bean buns. They're about to go bad.
真是个好孩子
That's my boy!
我说过那个梦是个好兆头
I told you that dream was a sign.
是哈 真高兴我做了这个梦…
Yeah. Glad I had it.
- 我是功夫大侠 - 我也是
- I'm a kung fu warrior! - Me, too!
- 山都连上天了 - 咱快点
- There's spots at the top. - Let's go.
加把劲
Come on. Come on!
就要到了
Almost there.
什么
What?
不会吧 不 不
No! Oh, no!
- 不好意思 阿宝 - 我们会给你带纪念品的
- Sorry, Po. - We'll bring you back a souvenir.
不 我要自己带纪念品下来
No. I'll bring me back a souvenir.
这是历史性的一天
It is an historic day.
是吧 乌龟大师？
Isn't it, Master Oogway?
没错 我还怕我不能活着等到这天
Yes, and one I feared I would not live to see.
你的徒弟们准备好了吗？
Are your students ready?
好了 乌龟大师
Yes, Master Oogway.
老朋友 你得明白
Know this, old friend.
不管我选了谁 不仅是给山谷带来平和
Whomever I choose will not only bring peace to the valley…
也是给你
…but also to you.
比武大会现在开始
Let the tournament begin!
耶！
Yeah.
不！等等
No, no, wait!
我来了！等等！
I'm coming! Wait, wait!
先别关
Yes!
嗨 把门开开！
Hey! Open the door!
让我进去！
Let me in!
平和谷的居民们
Oitizens of the Valley of Peace.
我深感荣幸 为你们介绍 娇虎
it is my great honor to present to you… Tigress!
灵蛇 仙鹤 金猴 螳螂
Viper! Orane! Monkey! Mantis!
「盖世五侠」
The Furious Five!
哇！盖世五侠！
Yeah, the Furious Five!
大侠们准备
Warriors, prepare!
等等 不 噢 门孔
Wait. No. Oh, peeky-hole.
- 准备比武 - 耶
- Ready for battle! - Yeah.
数千火舌
The Thousand Tongues of Fire.
哇噢 看看那个
Look at that.
嗨 别挡着我！
Hey! Get out of the way!
最后出场的是 娇虎大师
And finally Master Tigress!
相信我 居民们 你们将大开眼界
And believe me, citizens you have not seen anything yet.
我知道！
I know!
娇虎上场 为您表演 大战钢铁牛和他的绝命刀
Master Tigress! Face Iron OX and his Blades of Death.
我感觉到「神龙大侠」就在我们中间
I sense the Dragon Warrior is among us.
平和谷的居民们
Oitizens of the Valley of Peace,
乌龟大师现在要选出「神龙大侠」了
Master Oogway will now choose the Dragon Warrior!
什么？不不 等等！
Oh, no! No, no, wait!
有了
Yeah.
阿宝
Po!
你在干什么？
What are you doing?!
你说我在干什么？别…别吹！
What does it look like I'm doing?! Stop!
我要去看「神龙大侠」！
I'm going to see the Dragon Warrior!
可我不懂 你才做了面条梦啊
But I don't understand. You finally had the noodle dream!
我骗你的 老爸 我没梦见面条
I lied. I don't dream about noodles, Dad.
我爱功夫！
I love kung fu!
算了吧 儿子 还是回家卖面吧
Come on, son. Let's get back to work.
好吧
OK.
回来！
Come back!
什么情况
What's going on?
这是哪儿
Where…?
你指什么
What are you pointing…?
哦 对不起
OK. Sorry.
我只是想看看谁才是「神龙大侠」
I just wanted to see who the Dragon Warrior was.
真有意思啊
How interesting.
大师 您是指我吗？
Master, are you pointing at me?
- 他 - 谁？
- Him. - Who?
- 你 - 我？
- You. - Me?
上苍降「神龙大侠」给我们！
The universe has brought us the Dragon Warrior!
- 什么？- 什么？！
- What? - What?!
- 什么？！- 什么？！
- What?! - What?!
停下！等等！谁叫你们去的！
Stop, wait! Who told you to…?
乌龟大师 等等
Master Oogway, wait.
那只又肥又胖的熊猫怎么可能是神龙大侠
That flabby panda can't possibly be the answer to our problem.
你正要指娇虎的时候 那只破烂熊猫从天而降
You were about to point at Tigress and that thing fell in front of her!
这纯属意外！
That was just an accident!
世上无意外
There are no accidents.
请您原谅 师父 我们让您失望了
Forgive us, Master. We have failed you.
不 要是明天那熊猫还没打退堂鼓
No. If the panda has not quit by morning,
那是我让你们失望了
then I will have failed you.
等一下！我是来送信的
Wait! Wait, wait, wait! I bring a message…
替师父大师而来
…from Master Shifu.
什么？！
What?!
守卫加倍
"Double the guard?!"
警戒加倍
"Extra precautions?!"
你的天牢还不够严密
"Your prison may not be adequate?!"
你怀疑我天牢的安全？
You doubt my prison security?!
绝对没有
Absolutely not.
师父这么说 我就是个传话的
Shifu does. I'm just the messenger.
那么请你代我传个话给师父
I'll give you a message for your Master Shifu.
从桃岗天牢越狱 绝无可能！
Escape from Ohorh-Gom prison is impossible!
叹为观止吧？
Lmpressive, isn't it?
是 是 叹为观止
It's very impressive.
相当的叹为观止
进道出路 只有一条
One way in, one way out.
千名守卫 只为一囚
One thousand guards and one prisoner.
没错 只是那个囚徒是…
Yes, except that prisoner…
大龙
…is Tai Lung.
送我们下去
Take us down.
你要干什么
What are you doing?
噢 我的天哪
Oh, my.
看看 这就是大龙
Behold Tai Lung.
我…我还是待在这儿吧
I'm just gonna wait right here.
没什么好担心的 万无一失
It's nothing to worry about. It's perfectly safe.
弩弓待命
Orossbows! At the ready!
弩弓？
Orossbows?
嗨 牛人 你听说了吗？
Hey, tough guy, did you hear?
乌龟要把神龙卷轴传人了 别想了 反正不会是你
Oogway's giving someone the Dragon Scroll, and it's not gonna be you.
别把他惹恼了
Don't get him mad.
他又能怎么着 我已经把他捆结实了
What's he gonna do about it? I've got him completely immobilized.
喔 我是不是踩到小猫咪的尾巴了？
Did I step on the wittle kitty's tail?
够了 我看够了
I'm good. I've seen enough.
我会跟师父说没啥可担心的
I'll tell Shifu he has nothing to worry about.
当然不用担心
No, he doesn't.
我会告诉他的
I'll tell him that.
咱们能走了吗？
Can we please go now?
神龙大侠！神龙大侠！
Dragon Warrior! Dragon Warrior!
等一下
Wait a second!
我想这是个小误会 大家都以为我是…
I think there's been a slight mistake. Everyone seems to think that I'm…
奇侠圣殿！不会吧！
The Sacred Hall of Warriors! No way!
瞧瞧这地儿
Look at this place.
飞天犀牛大师的盔甲 还有货真价实的战斗破损！
Master Flying Rhino's armor with authentic battle damage!
英雄之刃！
The Sword of Heroes!
据说吹毛断发 看看都会受伤
Said to be so sharp you can cut yourself just by looking.
隐形的命运之杖！
The Invisible Trident of Destiny!
我只见过这画的临摹版
I've only seen paintings of that painting.
不会吧
No!
传说中的英灵窃语之瓮
The legendary Urn of Whispering Warriors.
据说里面有整个天书军团的灵魂
Said to contain the souls of the entire Tenshu Army.
你们好
Hello.
你观光完毕了吗？
Have you finished sight-seeing?
对不起 我该先来看你
Sorry, I should have come to you first.
我的耐心有限
My patience is wearing thin.
不过 看起来你也没法去哪儿
Well, I mean, it's not like you were going anywhere.
- 你能转过身来吗？- 当然
- Would you turn around? - Sure.
嗨 这样怎么样
How's it going?
你是怎么让五千… 师父大师
How do you get 5, 000… Master Shifu!
有人把这个打碎了
Someone… broke that.
但我会把它黏好的 你有没有…
But I'll fix it. Do you have some…
…胶水？
…glue?
啊，扎手了
A splinter.
你就是那个传说中的「神龙大侠」？
So you're the legendary Dragon Warrior?
- 我想是吧 - 错！
- I guess so. - Wrong!
你不是也不可能是神龙大侠 除非
You are not the Dragon Warrior. You will never be the Dragon Warrior until…
除非你掌握了神龙卷轴里的秘密
…you have learned the secret of the Dragon Scroll.
那我怎么上去呢
So, how does this work?
你有梯子或者蹦床或者…
Do you have a ladder or a trampoline, or…?
你想的太简单了 我会把那无限力量的秘密
You think it's that easy? That I'll just hand you the secret.
- 就这么交给你？- 不是的 我…
- to limitless power? - No, I…
一个人必须先达到功夫的最高境界
One must first master the highest level of kung fu.
而像你这样的是不可能了
And that is impossible if that one is someone like you.
像我这样？
Someone like me?
没错 瞧瞧你 这肥臀 这肥胳膊
Yes, look at you! This fat butt! Flabby arms!
啊 这些赘肉可都娇贵的很呢
Those are sensitive in the flabby parts.
还有这滑天下之大稽的大肚皮
And this ridiculous belly.
还有 一点儿也不讲卫生
And utter disregard for personal hygiene.
慢着 这么说可有点过分了
Now, wait a minute. That's uncalled for.
别站这么近 口臭都出来了
Don't stand that close. I can smell your breath.
听着 乌龟大师说我是…
Listen, Oogway said I was…
啊 巫师指 别用巫师指
The WuXi Finger Hold. Not the WuXi Finger Hold!
噢 你知道这个指法
Oh, you know this hold?
第三王朝时 巫师大师发明的
Developed by Master WuXi in the Third Dynasty.
那你一定知道 一旦弯下小指会发生什么了
Then you know what happens when I fleX my pinky.
- 别 千万别 - 你知道最难办的是什么吗？
- No, no! - You know the hardest part of this?
就是清理你的尸骨残骸
The hardest part is cleaning up afterwards.
是的 没错 别激动
OK, OK, take it easy.
那仔细听着 熊猫
Now listen closely, panda.
乌龟大师也许选了你 可当我找上你
Oogway may have picked you, but when I'm through with you,
我向你保证 你会希望 他选的不是你！清楚了吗？
I promise you, you're going to wish he hadn't! Are we clear?
清楚了 一清二楚 十分清楚
Yeah, we're clear. We're so clear.
很好 呵呵
Good.
我都等不及要开始了
I can't wait to get started.
- 开始吧 - 等等
- Let's begin. - Wait, wait, wait.
什么？
What?
- 现在吗？- 就现在！
- Now? - Yes, now.
除非你认为了不起的乌龟大师错了 而你也不是「神龙大侠」
Unless the great Oogway was wrong and you are not the Dragon Warrior.
好吧
Oh, OK, well…
我不知道我能不能… 把那些招式都比划出来
I don't know if I can do all of those moves.
不试试 又怎么能知道呢
Well, if we don't try we'll never know, will we?
是啊 但能不能从更合适我这个级别的开始
Yeah, it's just, maybe we can find something more suited to my level.
那你的级别又是什么呢？
What level is that?
你知道…我不是大师
Well, I'm not a master, but…
不如从零级开始 零级
…let's just start at zero. Level zero.
不 从来没有零级的说法
No. There is no such thing as level zero.
- 嘿 也许我可以从那开始 - 那个？
- Maybe I can start with that. - That?
我们用来训练孩子 天热的时候还用来顶门
We use that for training children and propping the door open when it's hot.
可要是你坚持的话…
But if you insist…
喔 是「盖世五侠」！
The Furious Five!
你们可比功夫公仔大多了 除了你 螳螂 你还是那么大
You're bigger than your action figures. EXcept, you, Mantis. You're the same.
开始吧 熊猫 让我们看看你的能耐
Go ahead, panda. Show us what you can do.
你们就在这看我打？还是我应该等你们都回去再开始…
Are they gonna watch, or should I wait till they get back to work?
出招
Hit it.
好吧 我刚吃完东西 还在消化
OK, yeah. I mean, I just ate. So I'm still digesting.
所以我的功夫可能不像过一会儿那么好
So my kung fu might not be as good as… later on.
快出招！
Just hit it.
好吧
All right.
你算老几啊？有我在这儿你啥都不算
What you got? You got nothing 'cause I got it right here.
你找我朋友的茬？准备受死吧
You picking on my friends? Get ready to feel thunder.
看我佛山无影脚 你没辙了吧？
I'm coming at you with crazy feet. What you gonna do about crazy feet?
来啊 给你来个移形幻影 没见识过熊猫功夫吧
Come on. I'm a blur. You've never seen bear style.
你就知道螳臂
You've only seen praying mantis.
猴拳
Or monkey style.
我还会金蛇狂舞
Or I could come at you snickety-snake.
你能出招吗？！
Would you hit it!
好吧 好吧
All right. All right.
再来一次 重点儿打
Why don't you try again? A little harder.
怎样…啊
How's that?
疼死我了！
That hurts.
这比我想得可简单多了
This will be easier than I thought.
我感到有点想吐！
I'm feeling a little nauseous!
这么硬！
Those are hard!
我的命根子
My tenders.
我表现如何
How did I do?
算得上零级了
There is now a level zero.
- 简直无语 - 没错
- There's no words. - No denying that.
真不懂乌龟大师怎么想的
What was Master Oogway thinking?
那可怜的孩子 差点把自己弄死
The poor guy's gonna get himself killed.
他太「无敌」了！
He is so mighty!
「神龙大侠」坐在火球上从天而降！
The Dragon Warrior fell out of the sky on a ball of fire!
举手投足 地动山摇！
When he walks, the very ground shakes!
本以为乌龟大师会选一个会功夫的
One would think Master Oogway would choose someone who knew kung fu.
没错 起码是一个能够到脚趾头的
Yeah, or could at least touch his toes.
至少也要能看到自己的脚趾头吧
Or even see his toes.
不错 都睡了
OK.
很好 就这样
Great.
嗨 你醒啦
Hi. You're up.
这下是了
I am now.
我只是
I was just…
不简单的一天哈
Some day, huh?
功夫可够累人的哈 你肱二头肌酸不酸？
That kung fu stuff is hard work, right? Are your biceps sore?
今天已经是又长又失望的一天了 所以…
I've had a long and rather disappointing day, so…
我差不多也该睡觉了
Yeah, I should probably get to sleep now.
- 对对 当然 - 谢谢
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. Of course. - OK, thanks.
我只是… 我可是你们的超级粉丝哦
It's just… Man, I'm such a big fan!
泣河一战 你们实在太牛了
You guys were amazing at the Battle of Weeping River.
你们以一挡千 你们毫无惧意 你们如同…
Outnumbered a thousand to one but you didn't stop. You just…
哦 不好意思
Sorry about that.
听着 你不属于这儿
Look, you don't belong here.
呃 我知道 说的没错
I know. I know. You're right.
我没啥… 我只是…
I don't have… I just…
我一生都梦想着…
My whole life I dreamed of…
不 我指你不属于「这儿」 我指这个房间 这是我的房间
No, I meant you don't belong here. I mean, in this room. This is my room.
仙鹤产权所有
Property of Orane.
哦 确实 确实
OK. Right, right.
那么…你想睡觉了
So, you want to get to sleep.
- 是的 - 我妨碍你了
- Yeah. - I'm keeping you up.
明天还有要事呢
We got big things tomorrow.
好吧 你很彪悍！我就说这么多 拜拜
All right. You're awesome. Last thing I'm gonna say. Bye-bye.
你刚说什么？
What was that?
我什么都没说
I didn't say anything.
好的 晚安
OK. All right. Good night.
好梦！
Sleep well.
貌似有点尴尬
That seemed a little awkward.
娇虎大师！没想吵醒你
Master Tigress! I didn't mean to wake you.
- 你不属于这里！- 是的 当然
- You don't belong here. - Yeah, of course.
这是你的房间
This is your room.
我的意思是 你不配待在翡翠宫
I mean, you don't belong in the Jade Palace.
你让功夫蒙羞
You're a disgrace to kung fu,
如果你对我们 还有我们的事业存有敬重
and if you have any respect for who we are and what we do,
明早前 你就该走人
you will be gone by morning.
超级粉丝哦
Big fan!
看来你找到了圣智桃树啊
I see you have found the Sacred Peach Tree of Heavenly Wisdom.
这就是？抱歉我以为它就是棵普通桃树
Is that what this is? Sorry. I thought it was just a regular peach tree.
我能理解 你不开心的时候就会吃东西
I understand. You eat when you are upset.
不开心？我没不开心啊 什么让你认为我不开心了？
Upset? I'm not upset. What makes you think I'm upset.
那你为什么不开心呢？
So why are you so upset?
我可能是功夫史上最烂的
I probably sucked more today than anyone in the history of kung fu.
中国史上最烂的 烂人史上也是最烂的！
In the history of China. In the history of sucking!
可能
Probably.
看看「盖世五侠」！你该看看 他们对我恨之入骨啊！
And the Five! Man, you should've seen them! They totally hate me.
不假
Totally.
师父怎么可能把我变成「神龙大侠」啊？
How is Shifu ever going to turn me into the Dragon Warrior?
我一点也不像「五侠」
I mean, I'm not like the Five.
我没爪子 没翅膀 也没毒牙
I've got no claws, no wings, no venom.
就连螳螂 也有那些…镰刀
Even Mantis has those… thingies.
唉 也许我就该一走了之 回家煮面
Maybe I should just quit and go back to making noodles.
回家？不回家？
Quit, don't quit.
煮面？不煮面？
Noodles, don't noodles.
你太在意过去曾怎样 将来会怎样
You are too concerned with what was and what will be.
有句谚语说得好
There's a saying:
昨天已是历史
Yesterday is history,
明天还很神秘
tomorrow is a mystery,
但是今天是一个礼物
but today is a gift.
这就是为什么要把它叫做「当下」
That is why it is called the present.
- 噢 不会吧 - 发生什么了？
- Oh, no! - What's happening?!
去你的战斗位置 快 快
To your battle stations! Go! Go! Go!
弩弓发射！
Fire crossbows!
发射！
Fire!
大龙越狱了！我必须去警告师父
Tai Lung is free! I must warn Shifu.
- 你哪也去不了！他也一样！- 放开我！
- Not going anywhere! Neither is he! - Let go of me!
把它拉起来
Bring it up!
等等 先放下来
Wait! Bring it back!
- 他朝这来了 - 他过不来的 弓箭手
- He's coming this way! - He won't get far. Archers!
我们死翘翘了 死得很翘很翘了！
We're dead. So very, very dead.
还没呢 至少现在还没！
Not yet we're not. Now!
- 现在能跑了么 - 能了
- Can we run now? - Yes.
我很高兴师父派你来
I'm glad Shifu sent you.
我还以为都把我忘了呢
I was beginning to think I'd been forgotten.
飞回去跟他们说
Fly back there and tell them…
真正的「神龙大侠」 要回家了
…the real Dragon Warrior is coming home.
早上好 大师
Good morning, Master!
熊猫！
Panda!
起床！
Wake up!
他果然走了
He's quit.
我们现在做什么 熊猫走了 谁会成为「神龙大侠」呢？
What do we do now, with the panda gone? Who will be the Dragon Warrior?
我们能做的 就是勤加练习 假以时日
All we can do is resume our training and trust that in time,
真正的「神龙大侠」便会脱颖而出
the true Dragon Warrior will be revealed.
你在这干吗？
What are you doing here?!
早上好 大师
Hi! Good morning, Master!
我想先热热身
I thought I'd warm up a little.
你卡住了
You're stuck.
卡住了？什么 哪有？
Stuck? Nah. What? Stuck?
没有 我只是在… 好吧 我卡住了
Nah. This is one of my… Yeah, I'm stuck.
- 去帮他 - 受不了
- Help him. - Oh, dear.
我数到三！一 二
Maybe on three. One, two…
…三
…three.
- 谢谢 - 别提这事
- Thank you. - Don't mention it.
- 不 我真的很感激… - 永远别提！
- No, really, I appreciate… - Ever.
你真以为你能一夜练成劈叉？
You actually thought you could learn to do a full split in one night?
这可是数年苦练 才习得的柔韧
It takes years to develop one's flexibility!
再加以数载 才能用于实战
And years longer to apply it in combat!
把-那-放-下-来！
Put that down!
我们收集的纪念品 只会是残肢断臂
The only souvenirs we collect here are bloody knuckles and broken bones.
酷 棒极了！
Yeah! EXcellent.
让我们开始吧
Let's get started.
- 你准备好了吗？- 我打小就准备…啊！
- Are you ready? - I was born re…
真不好意思 我以为你说的是你早已准备好了呢
I'm sorry, brother. I thought you said you were ready.
真是太酷了 再来
That was awesome! Let's go again!
我一直都对你手下留情 熊猫 但到此为止
I've been taking it easy on you, panda. But no more.
你下一个对手 就是我
Your next opponent will be me.
太棒了 来吧
All right! Yeah, let's go!
上前一步
Step forth.
取胜的两个诀窍就是 找到对手的软肋
The true path to victory is to find your opponent's weakness…
并让他痛不欲生
…and make him suffer for it.
爽
Oh, yeah!
借力打力
To take his strength and use it against him…
直到他倒地不起
…until he finally falls…
或求饶认输
…or quits.
真的大侠绝不言弃
A real warrior never quits.
别担心 大师 我永远不会放弃的！
Don't worry, Master. I will never quit!
如果他够聪明 他不会再爬上来了
If he's smart he won't come back up those steps.
可他会上来的
But he will.
他不会放弃的 是吧？
He's not going to quit, is he?
我能告诉你的是 他不会放弃弹跳的
He's not going to quit bouncing I'll tell you that.
我记得你说针灸会让我好受些
I thought you said acupuncture would make me feel better.
相信我 会的
Trust me, it will.
只是不容易找准你的穴位 都是些…
It's just not easy finding the right nerve points under all this…
- 脂肪？- 毛皮 我是想说毛皮的
- Fat? - Fur. I was going to say fur.
才怪
Sure you were.
我怎么会用体型来评价一个大侠 看看我
Who am I to judge a warrior based on his size? Look at me.
我在这里
I'm over here.
也许你得再看看这个
Maybe you should look at this again.
噢 好吧
Oh, OK.
住手 住手…啊！
Stop it. Stop!
我知道师父大师是在激励我
I know Master Shifu is trying to inspire me and all…
要不是我了解他 我还以为他是想撵我走
…but if I didn't know better I'd say he was trying to get rid of me.
我知道他看上去有点无情
I know he can seem kind of heartless…
可他原本不是这样的
…but he wasn't always like that.
传说
According to legend.
很久以前 师父也曾笑口常开
there was once a time when Master Shifu actually used to smile.
- 不可能 - 真的
- No! - Yes.
那是在…之前
But that was before.
在什么之前？
Before what?
在大龙之前
Before Tai Lung.
我们不该提起他的
We're not really supposed to talk about him.
要是他打算留下 就该知道
Well, if he's going to stay here he should know.
各位 各位 我知道大龙
Guys, guys, I know about Tai Lung.
他是有史以来第一个 学会了师父千般武艺的徒弟
He was a student. The first ever to master the thousand scrolls of kung fu.
然后他变坏了 再然后…就蹲大牢了…
And then he turned bad and now he's in jail.
他不只是个徒弟
He wasn'tjust a student.
师父捡到他时 他还在襁褓之中
Shifu found him as a cub…
师父抚养他长大 视同己出
…and he raised him as his son.
当发现那小子天生就是武学奇才时
And when the boy showed talent in kung fu…
师父倾其所能悉心教导
…Shifu trained him.
信任他 跟他说必成大器
He believed in him. He told him he was destined for greatness.
大龙他永远不满足
It was never enough for Tai Lung.
他想得到神龙卷轴
He wanted the Dragon Scroll.
可乌龟大师洞察到了他心中的黑暗 拒绝传给他
But Oogway saw darkness in his heart and refused.
盛怒之下 大龙血洗山谷
Outraged, Tai Lung laid waste to the valley.
他试图强行夺取卷轴
He tried to take the scroll by force.
师父不得不斩除自己种下的祸根
And Shifu had to destroy what he had created.
可他怎么忍心呢？
But how could he?
师父之前从没像爱大龙那样爱过别人
Shifu loved Tai Lung like he had never loved anyone before.
或许 从那之后也没有
Or since.
而现在他有机会 来拨乱返正
And now he has a chance to make things right.
训练真正的「神龙大侠」
To train the true Dragon Warrior.
却碰到了你
And he's stuck with you.
这只又肥又胖视练武如儿戏的熊猫
A big fat panda who treats it like a joke.
够了！
That is it!
等等 我的错！我不小心扎到了他的面部穴位
Wait! My fault! I accidentally tweaked his facial nerve.
好像心脏也被扎停了
And may have also stopped his heart.
平心静气
Inner peace.
平心…
Inner…
平心静气
Inner peace.
谁在呼扇呼扇的？给我安静！
Would whoever is making that flapping sound quiet down?!
平心…
Inner…
噢 小曾
Oh, Zeng.
太好了
Excellent.
我现在正需要一些好消息
I could use some good news right now.
大师 大师
Master! Master!
我有一个… 一个… 很坏的消息
I have… It's… It's very bad news.
师父
Shifu.
消息就是消息 没有好坏之分
There is just news. There is no good or bad.
大师 你的幻相…你的幻相应验了！
Master, your vision. Your vision was right.
大龙越狱了 他正在赶来！
Tai Lung has broken out of prison. He's on his way.
这还真是坏消息
That is bad news…
如果你不相信「神龙大侠」可以阻止他的话
…if you do not believe that the Dragon Warrior can stop him.
那只熊猫？大师 那熊猫可不是什么「神龙大侠」
The panda? Master that panda is not the Dragon Warrior.
他根本不该在这儿 那只是个巧合
He wasn't meant to be here! It was an accident.
没有巧合
There are no accidents.
是的我知道 你已经说过…
Yes, I know. You've said that already.
- 两遍了 - 这也不是偶然.
- Twice. - Well, that was no accident, either.
三遍了
Thrice.
我的老朋友
My old friend,
阿宝没法完成他的使命 你也一样
the panda will never fulfill his destiny, nor you yours,
除非假象不再蒙蔽你的眼睛
until you let go of the illusion of control.
假象
Illusion?
没错 看看这棵树 师父
Yes. Look at this tree, Shifu.
我无法强迫它随时开花
I cannot make it blossom when it suits me,
也不能令它提前结果
nor make it bear fruit before its time.
但是 有些事情我们可以控制
But there are things we can control.
我可以左右果子何时落地
I can control when the fruit will fall.
我还可以左右种子…
And I can control…
种于何地
…where to plant the seed.
这可不是假象 大师
That is no illusion, Master.
没错
Yes.
即便如此 无论你做什么
But no matter what you do,
这种子终会长成桃树
that seed will grow to be a peach tree.
你也许想要苹果或是橘子 但你能得到的只能是桃子
You may wish for an apple or an orange but you will get a peach.
但是桃子不能打败大龙
But a peach cannot defeat Tai Lung!
也许可以呢
Maybe it can.
只要你愿意对其谆谆教导
If you are willing to guide it.
悉心培养
To nurture it.
心存信念
To believe in it.
但是 得怎么做呢？要怎么做呢？
But how? How?
我需要你的帮助 大师
I need your help, Master.
不需要 你只需要相信
No, you just need to believe.
答应我 师父
Promise me, Shifu.
答应我你会相信
Promise me you will believe.
我…尽量
I will try.
很好
Good.
我的时辰到了
My time has come.
你得孤身前行了
You must continue yourjourney without me.
什… 什…你说什么…等等
What are you…? Wait!
大师！
Master!
不要丢下我一个
You can't leave me!
你必须相信
You must believe.
大师！
Master!
吓人吧？我说 就算你是豺狼…
Scary? Yeah, so I'm like "Fine, you may be a wolf,
或是福建第一恶霸
you may be the scariest bandit in Haijin Province…
可你给小费太小气啦
…but you're a lousy tipper."
真的？那你是怎么活着回来的？
Really? So how did you get out of there alive?
我是说… 我没有真的说出口
I mean, I didn't actually say that…
我只是心里
…but I thought it…
这么想
…in my mind.
他要是会读心术的话 一定会说：「大胆！」
If he could read my mind he'd be, like, "What?"
面来咯 希望你们会喜欢
Order up! Hope you like it.
- 味道好极了 - 得了吧
- This is really good! - No, come on.
你得尝尝我老爸的私酿密汤 只有他知道秘方
Try my dad's Secret Ingredient Soup. He actually knows the secret ingredient.
说什么呢 这味道棒极了
What do you mean? This is amazing!
- 你可真会煮 - 真希望嘴巴大一点
- You're a really good cook. - I wish my mouth was bigger.
娇虎 快尝尝
Tigress, you've got to try this.
相传「神龙大侠」单靠银杏甘露
It is said that the Dragon Warrior can survive for months.
和日月精华 就能活好几个月
on nothing but the dew of ginkgo leaf and the energy of the universe.
我猜我的身体还没意识到它成了「神龙大侠」呢
I guess my body doesn't know it's the Dragon Warrior yet.
光靠甘露和精华可没法活
I'm gonna need a lot more than dew and universe juice.
- 笑啥？- 没啥 师父大师
- What? - Nothing… Master Shifu.
你永远都成不了「神龙大侠」 除非你减500磅膘 刷干净牙
Never be the Dragon Warrior unless you lose 500 pounds and brush your teeth!
吵什么吵？！笑声 我听都没听过
What is that noise you're making? Laughter? I never heard of it!
努力吧 熊猫 也许有一天
Work hard, panda, and maybe someday…
你可以拥有像我一样的耳朵
…you will have ears like mine.
还真像
That's good.
耳朵 不好笑吗？我觉得挺逗的
Ears. It's not working for you? I thought they were pretty good.
是师父！
It's Shifu!
当然是师父 不然你以为我在模仿谁？
Of course it's Shifu. What do you think I'm doing?
噢… 师父大师
Master Shifu!
你们觉得好笑吗？
You think this is funny?
大龙越狱了 你们还跟个小孩子一样！
Tai Lung has escaped and you're acting like children!
- 什么？- 他是冲着「神龙卷轴」来的
- What? - He is coming for the Dragon Scroll,
而你是唯一可以阻止他的人
and you are the only one who can stop him.
哈哈 我说的没错吧 你还真不懂幽默
And I was saying you got no sense of humor.
要我…阻止大龙
I'm gonna… stop Tai Lung.
啥？！你当真？真要我去？
What? You're serious? And I have to…?
乌龟大师会阻止他的 就像他上次那样
Master Oogway will stop him like he did before, he'll do it again.
乌龟不能
Oogway cannot!
再也不能了
Not anymore.
我们唯一的希望就只剩下「神龙大侠」了
Our only hope is the Dragon Warrior.
- 靠这熊猫？- 就靠这熊猫
- The panda? - Yes, the panda!
师父 拜托 让我们来阻止大龙 这也是你教我们武功的目的
Master, please, let us stop Tai Lung. This is what you've trained us for.
不 打败大龙不是你的使命
No! It is not your destiny to defeat Tai Lung.
而是他的！
It is his!
人呢？
Where'd he go?
你不可以走 真的大侠是永不言弃的
You cannot leave! A real warrior never quits.
看看我
Watch me.
拜托
Come on.
我凭什么打败大龙 我连绕过你下山都做不到
How am I supposed to beat Tai Lung? I can't even beat you to the stairs.
你可以打败他 因为你是「神龙大侠」
You will beat him because you are the Dragon Warrior.
你不信这鬼话 你从没信过这鬼话
You don't believe that. You never believed that.
我初来乍到的时候 你不是想方设法把我踹走？
From the beginning you've tried to get rid of me.
没错 那是以前
Yes! I was.
但现在 我要你相信你的师父 就像我相信我的师父那样
But now I ask you to trust in your master as I have come to trust in mine.
你不是我师父 我也不是什么「神龙大侠」
You're not my master. And I'm not the Dragon Warrior.
那你为什么不放弃 你明知道我要赶你走 但你还是留下了
Then why didn't you quit?! You knew I wanted you gone, yet you stayed.
没错 我是留下了
Yeah, I stayed.
我留下是因为 每次你往我头上拍砖
I stayed because every time you threw a brick at my head,
或者说我难闻 是会让我伤心 但这些都赶不上以前
or said I smelled, it hurt but it could never hurt more,
过去天天浑浑噩噩 更让我伤心
than it did every day of my life just being me.
我留下 是因为我知道 要是还有人能改变我
I stayed because I thought if anyone could change me…
可以让我超越自己
…could make me… not me…
那个人就是你
…it was you.
全中国最了不起的功夫师父
The greatest kung fu teacher in all of China!
我可以改变你！
But I can change you!
我可以让你成为「神龙大侠」 我会做到的！
I can turn you into the Dragon Warrior! And I will!
拜托 大龙马上就要赶到了
Come on. Tai Lung is on his way here right now.
就算他要在路上耗上一百年
Even if it takes him a hundred years to get here, how are you…
你又怎么能把眼前这个肥仔训练成神龙大侠？
…gonna change this into the Dragon Warrior?
有办法吗？
How?
有吗？
- 没有了吧？- 我不知道
- How?! - I don't know!
我不知道
I don't know.
我就知道
That's what I thought.
养兵千日 用兵一时
This is what you trained me for.
娇虎！
Tigress!
别想拦我！
Don't try and stop me.
我们不是要拦你
We're not trying to stop you.
什么？
What?
我们是要跟你并肩作战
We're coming with you!
怎么啦？我不开心就吃 不行吗？
What? I eat when I'm upset, OK?
噢 不必解释
No need to explain.
我还以为是金猴呢 他总把杏仁饼干藏在架子最上面
I thought you might be Monkey. He hides his almond cookies on the top shelf.
别跟猴哥说
Don't tell Monkey.
- 看看你 - 我知道 我让你看了恶心
- Look at you. - Yeah, I know, I disgust you.
不 我是说 你是怎么爬上去的？
No, I mean, how did you get up there?
不晓得 我只是…
I don't know. I guess that…
不晓得 我只是想着饼干
I don't know. I was getting a cookie.
然后你就瞬间离地十尺
Yet you are ten feet off the ground.
而且还做出了完美的劈叉
And you have done a perfect spilt.
不是啦 这只是…
No, this? This is just…
误打误撞
…an accident.
根本就没有什么误打误撞
There are no accidents.
跟我来
Come with me.
我知道你为教我武功 故弄玄虚
I know you're trying to be all mystical and kung fuey…
但也至少告诉我现在是去哪吧？
…but could you at least tell me where we're going?
你…
You dragged me…
让我累死累活爬上来…
…all the way out here…
就为了让我洗白白？
…for a bath?
熊猫
Panda…
这池神圣之泪可不是给你洗胳肢窝的
…we do not wash our pits in the Pool of Sacred Tears.
这池是…
The Pool of…
这是乌龟大师参透禅机的地方
This is where Oogway unraveled the mysteries…
两极调和 心无旁骛
…of harmony and focus.
这就是功夫的
This is the birthplace…
发源地
…of kung fu.
你想学功夫吗？
Do you want to learn kung fu?
当然
Yeah!
那么我就是你的师父
Then I am your master!
明白
OK!
不要哭
Don't cry.
好的
OK.
当你一心想着功夫
When you focus on kung fu,
想要心无杂念
when you concentrate…
你就会搞臭
…you stink.
不过那也许是我的错
Perhaps that is my fault.
我不该一成不变 像教导「五侠」一样教导你
I cannot train you the way I have trained the Five.
现在我明白了 要你学好武功
I now see that the way to get through to you…
就得靠这个
…is with this.
噢 太棒了 我快饿扁了
Oh, great, 'cause I am hungry.
很好
Good.
等你练完 就能吃了
When you have been trained, you may eat.
开始吧
Let us begin.
你先请
After you, panda.
这么简单？
Just like that?
不需要仰卧起坐？不需要十里长跑？
No sit-ups? No ten-mile hike?
我起誓教你武功 你也学有所成 你可以尽情享用了
I vowed to train you, and you have been trained. You are free to eat.
多吃点
Enjoy.
嘿
Hey!
我说了你可以尽情享用 来个饺子
I said you are free to eat. Have a dumpling.
你干嘛
Hey!
尽情享用
You are free to eat.
- 可以吗！？- 你说呢？！
- Am I?! - Are you?!
我不饿
I'm not hungry.
师父
Master.
砍断吊桥！
Cut it!
「神龙大侠」怎么没来？
Where's the Dragon Warrior?
你怎么知道我不是？
How do you know you're not looking at her?
你当我傻？
You think I'm a fool?
我知道你根本就不是神龙大侠 你们五个都不是
I know you're not the Dragon Warrior. None of you!
我听说了 他坐着火球从天而降
I heard how he fell out of the sky in a ball of fire.
他才是大侠 前无古人
That he's a warrior unlike anything the world has ever seen.
- 阿宝？- 那就是他的名字？阿宝
- Po? - So that is his name. Po.
我终于棋逢对手
Finally, a worthy opponent.
这场对决将流传万世
Our battle will be legendary!
我们来拉住 你去帮她
We've got this. Help her.
金猴！
Monkey!
快去
Go!
想啥呢
What was I thinking?!
螳螂！
Mantis!
快上！
Now!
师父把你们教得不错
Shifu taught you well.
不过并没倾囊相授
But he didn't teach you everything.
你表现不错 熊猫
You have done well, panda.
表现不错？只是表现不错？
Done well? Done well?
我表现彪悍！
I've done awesome!
真英雄无不谦逊有加
The mark of a true hero is humility.
话虽这样说 你表现确实…
But, yes, you have done…
彪悍
…awesome.
伙计们？是他们！他们死了！
Guys? Guys?! They're dead!
不对 还有气 睡着了？眼睛睁着呢
No, they're breathing. They're asleep? No, their eyes are open.
我们根本不是对手 都被点穴了
We were no match for his nerve attach.
他越来越强了
He's gotten stronger.
谁？大龙吗？更强了？
Who? Tai Lung? Stronger?
他太快了
He's too fast!
不好意思 阿宝
Sorry, Po.
我以为我们能够阻止他的
I thought we could stop him.
他本来可以杀了你们的
He could have killed you.
那他为什么没呢？
Why didn't he?
让你们活着回来引发恐惧 但这招不会得逞的
So you could come back and strike fear into our hearts. But it won't work.
这招可能有用… 有点用…
It might. I mean, a little.
好吧 我真被吓到了
I'm pretty scared.
你可以打败他的 熊猫
You can defeat him, panda!
你在说笑吧？连他们都不行
Are you kidding? If they can't?!
他们可是盖世「五」侠 我只是「一个」我而已
They're five masters. I'm just one me.
但是 你拥有一样任何人都没有的东西
But you will have the one thing that no one else does.
你真的相信我已经准备好了？
You really believe I'm ready?
是的
You are…
阿宝
…Po.
修习神龙卷轴吧
Behold the Dragon Scroll.
现在它是你的了
It is yours.
等等 如果我读了它的话会怎么样
Wait. What happens when I read it?
没人知道 但据传说 你能听到蝴蝶振翅之声
Legend says you will be able to hear a butterfly's wing beat.
真的？酷！
Really? That's cool.
是的 能在至暗之洞中明察秋毫
Yes. And see light in the deepest cave.
能感应周身天地的一举一动
You will feel the universe in motion around you.
哇哦！我能打穿墙吗？
Can I punch through walls?
- 我能连做四个后空翻吗？- 心无杂念
- Do a quadruple back flip? - Focus.
- 我能…？- 心无杂念
- Will I…? - Focus.
- 心无杂念 - 哦 好的 好的
- Focus. - Oh, yeah, yeah.
阿宝 读吧 完成你的使命
Read it, Po, and fulfill your destiny.
读吧 成为…
Read it and become…
「神龙大侠」！
…the Dragon Warrior.
根本打不开
It's impossible to open.
别那么紧，快开开吧
OK. Come on, baby. Come on now.
谢谢
Thank you.
也许是我刚才已经弄松了
I probably loosened it up for you though.
好了 我要看了
OK, here goes.
- 怎么是空白 - 啥？
- It's blank. - What?!
- 不信 你看 - 禁止旁人看的
- Here, look. - No, I am forbidden to look upon…
还真是空白 我…
Blank. I don't…
我想不通
I don't understand.
好吧 就是说
OK. So, like…
乌龟也不过就是只疯癫老龟
…Oogway was just a crazy old turtle after all.
不 乌龟大师的智慧无人能及
No. Oogway was wiser than us all.
拜托 面对现实吧 他只不过是碰巧选上了我
Oh, come on! Face it he picked me by accident.
我当然不是什么「神龙大侠」 开什么玩笑
Of course I'm not the Dragon Warrior. Who am I kidding?
可谁来阻止大龙呢？
But who will stop Tai Lung?
他会毁了一切 并杀了每个人的
He'll destroy everything and everyone.
不会的
No.
疏散整个山谷 你们必须保护村民们免受大龙的残暴
Evacuate the valley. You must protect the villagers from Tai Lung's rage.
- 那您怎么办呢 师父？- 我来迎战他
- What about you, Master? - I will fight him.
- 什么？- 我能拖多久就拖多久
- What? - I can hold him off long enough.
这样大家都能全身而退
for everyone to escape.
但是 师父 他会杀了你的
But, Shifu, he'll kill you.
那就算我为过错付出的代价吧
Then I will finally have paid for my mistake.
都听我说
Listen to me, all of you.
没有我 你们也要继续走下去
It is time for you to continue yourjourney without me.
身为你们的师父 我十分自豪
I am very proud to have been your master.
我们必须让他们平安转移
We've got to get them out safely.
来 小家伙 我们去找妈妈
Come, little one. Let's find your mama.
灵蛇 集合村子南边的人 螳螂 你去村北
Viper, gather the southern farmers. Mantis, the north.
仙鹤 掌灯引路
Orane, light the way.
看 那就是「神龙大侠」
Look, it's the Dragon Warrior.
嗨 老爸
Hey, Dad.
阿宝！
Po!
回来就好 儿子
Good to have you back, son.
回来…就好…
Good to be back.
我们走吧 阿宝
Let's go, Po.
看来 我们该规划下一家面馆了
So for our next shop it's time to face it…
今后做面 菜要切成丁
…the future of noodles is dice-cut vegetables…
不再切成丝了
…no longer slices.
我还在想 趁着这次
Also, I was thinking, maybe this time.
我们弄个大厨房 你就不用猫着腰了
we'll have a kitchen you can actually stand up in.
怎么样？
You like that?
阿宝 我很遗憾 事不如愿
Po, I'm sorry if things didn't work out.
也许你就没那个命
It just wasn't meant to be.
阿宝 忘了这些不快吧
Po, forget everything else.
你真正的命运还在等你呢
Your destiny still awaits.
我们是面条世家 血管里流淌着面汤
We are noodle folk. Broth runs deep through our veins.
我不知道 老爸
I don't know, Dad.
说实话 有时我甚至不相信我是你儿子
Honestly, sometimes I can't believe I'm actually your son.
阿宝
Po…
我想是时候告诉你 一些很久以前
…I think it's time I told you something I should have told you…
就该告诉你的事了
…a long time ago.
好的
OK.
我那秘之又秘私酿密汤的配方…
The secret ingredient of my Secret Ingredient Soup.
…靠近点…秘之又秘的配方就是…
Come here. The secret ingredient is…
啥都没
…nothing.
听到了么 啥都没！
You heard me. Nothing!
根本就没什么秘之又秘的配方！
There is no secret ingredient!
等等 一切只不过是普通的面汤？
Wait, wait. It's just plain old noodle soup?
没加什么秘方酱汁 或者其他什么特别的东西？
You don't add some kind of special sauce or something?
没那必要 想让一件东西特别 你只要相信那是特别的就够了
Don't have to. To make something special, you just believe it's special.
根本没有秘方
There is no secret ingredient.
我回家来了 师父
I have come home, Master.
这里不再是你家 我也不再是你师父
This is no longer your home. And I am no longer your master.
是啊 你已经另有新宠了
Oh, yes. You have a new favorite.
那么 阿宝人呢？
So where is this Po?
我把他吓跑了吗？
Did I scare him off?
这是你我之间的战斗
This battle is between you and me.
那么 就如你所言吧
So, that is how it's going to be.
必须如我所言
That is how it must be.
我在大牢里蹲了20年 就因为你的懦弱！
I rotted in jail for 20 years because of your weakness!
尊从师命 怎叫软弱
Obeying your master is not weakness!
你原本知道的 我才是「神龙大侠」
You knew I was the Dragon Warrior.
你一直都知道
You always knew.
但是当乌龟说「非也」 你做了什么？
But when Oogway said otherwise what did you do?
你做什么了？
What did you do?!
什么都没做！
Nothing!
你命中注定不是神龙大侠 那不是我的错！
You were not meant to be the Dragon Warrior! That was not my fault!
不是你的错？
Not your fault?!
是谁让我满怀梦想？
Who filled my head with dreams?!
是谁逼我练功练到骨错筋伤？
Who drove me to train until my bones cracked?!
又是谁害我当不成神龙大侠？
Who denied me my destiny?!
那件事并非我能决定
It was never my decision to make!
现在 你能了
It is now.
给-我-卷-轴！
Give me the scroll!
我宁可死
I would rather die.
我做的一切都是为了让你骄傲
All I ever did, I did to make you proud!
告诉我你有多骄傲 师父！
Tell me how proud you are, Shifu!
你说啊！
Tell me!
你说！
我…我一直都为你骄傲
I have… I have always been proud of you.
从一开始 我就
From the first moment, I've been…
为你骄傲
…proud of you.
正是这种骄傲
And it was my pride…
蒙蔽了我双眼
…that blinded me.
对你的溺爱 让我看不到你的变化
I loved you too much to see what you were becoming…
是因为我
…what I…
你才变成这样的
…was turning you into.
我…
I'm…
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我不要你的道歉
I don't want your apology.
我要卷轴！
I want my scroll!
什么！
What?!
卷轴去哪了？！
Where is it?!
神龙大侠早已带着神龙卷轴远走高飞了
Dragon Warrior has taken the scroll halfway across China by now.
你永远见不到那卷轴了 大龙
You will never see that scroll, Tai Lung.
永远
Never.
台阶太多了…
Stairs.
你是谁？
Who are you?
伙计 我就是「神龙大侠」
Buddy, I am the Dragon Warrior.
你？
You?
他？一只熊猫？
Him? He's a panda.
你就是只熊猫 你想怎么着，大家伙？一屁股坐死我？
You're a panda. What are you gonna do, big guy? Sit on me?
别把我惹毛了
Don't tempt me.
现在 我可要用这个了
Now. I'm gonna use this.
想要吗？来拿啊！
You want it? Come and get it.
终于到手
Finally!
那个卷轴是我的！
That scroll is mine!
快如闪电
Lightning!
卷轴给了他力量！
The scroll has given him power!
不！
No!
终于到手了 哦 太好了
Finally! Oh, yes.
神龙卷轴的力量 是我的！
The power of the Dragon Scroll is mine!
怎么是空的？！
It's nothing!
没关系 我第一次也没看出个所以然来
It's OK. I didn't get it the first time, either.
什么？
What?
根本没有秘方
There is no secret ingredient.
关键就在自己
It's just you.
停下
Stop it!
我都想尿尿了
I'm gonna pee.
别戳
Don't.
别… 别戳了
Don't! Don't!
你…
You…
不可能打败我
…can't defeat me.
你…
You…
你不过是只又肥…
…you're just a big…
…又胖的…
…fat…
熊猫！
…panda!
我不是什么又肥又胖的熊猫
I'm not a big fat panda.
我是独一无二的又肥又胖的熊猫
I'm the big fat panda.
巫师指？！
The WuXi Finger Hold!
噢 你知道这招啊
Oh, you know this hold?
你唬我 你在唬我 师父不会教你的
You're bluffing. You're bluffing. Shifu didn't teach you that.
当然
Nope.
我无师自通
I figured it out. Skadoosh.
看啊！
Look!
是「神龙大侠」
The Dragon Warrior.
那个可爱的大块头功夫大侠 就是我儿子！
That's my boy! That big lovely kung fu warrior is my son!
儿子
Yes!
谢谢你 老爸
Thanks, Dad.
嗨 伙计们
Hey, guys.
大师
Master.
Master?
师父大师
Master Shifu!
大师
Master!
师父 你还好吗？
Shifu, are you OK?!
阿宝
Po.
你还活着？
You're alive.
还是咱俩都死了？
Or we're both dead.
不 师父 我没死 我打败了大龙
No, Master, I didn't die. I defeated Tai Lung.
真的？
You did?
哇噢 正如乌龟所说
Wow. It is as Oogway foretold.
你就是「神龙大侠」
You are the Dragon Warrior.
你把平和
You have brought peace…
带给这个山谷
…to this valley…
也…
…and…
也带给了我
…and to me.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢谢你 阿宝
Thank you, Po.
谢谢… 谢谢…
Thank you. Thank you.
不不不 师父 别死啊！！
No! Master! No, no, no don't die, Shifu, please!
我没死 你个白痴！
I'm not dying, you idiot!
哦 「神龙大侠」
Ah. Dragon Warrior…
我只是在享受平和 终于平和了
…I am simply at peace. Finally.
噢 那我应该闭嘴？
So, I should stop talking?
最好是
If you can.
要不要…吃点啥？
Want to get something to eat?
好
Yeah.
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ Everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ Everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 你有如此高的天赋 ∮
∮ You are a natural ∮
∮ 但又为何不为人知 ∮
∮ Why is that so hard to see? ∮
∮ 或许太过在乎自己 ∮
∮ Maybe it's just because You keep on looking at me ∮
∮ 孤身之路远超想像 ∮
∮ The journey's a lonely one So much more than we know ∮
∮ 但你必须英勇前往 ∮
∮ But sometimes you've got to go And be your own hero ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ Everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 你是沙粒中的钻石 ∮
∮ You're a diamond in the rough A brilliant ball of clay ∮
∮ 努力下去必将成器 ∮
∮ You could be a work of art If you just go all the way ∮
∮ 只要你能坚持下去 ∮
∮ Now what would it take to break? I believe that you can bend ∮
∮ 战斗你一定能胜利 ∮
∮ Not only do you have to fight But you have got to win ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ 'Oause everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮
∮ 你是沙粒中的钻石 ∮
∮ You're a diamond in the rough A brilliant ball of clay ∮
∮ 努力下去必将成器 ∮
∮ You could be a work of art If you just go all the way ∮
∮ 只要你能坚持下去 ∮
∮ Now what would it take to break? I believe that you can bend ∮
∮ 战斗你一定能胜利 ∮
∮ Not only do you have to fight But you have got to win ∮
∮ 人人都爱比试武艺 ∮
∮ 'Oause everybody is kung fu fighting ∮
∮ 你的思想闪电难及 ∮
∮ Your mind becomes fast as lightning ∮
∮ 尽管前路有些恐惧 ∮
∮ Although the future is a little bit frightening ∮
∮ 你仍书写你的传奇 ∮
∮ It's the book of your life that you're writing ∮